<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Nature Communications | Open Source Toolkit</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/tag/nature-communications/</link><atom:link href="https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/tag/nature-communications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Nature Communications</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>CC BY SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/media/openneuroscience_logo_dark.svg</url><title>Nature Communications</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/tag/nature-communications/</link></image><item><title>Free-space transfer of comb-rooted optical frequencies over an 18 km open-air link</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/freespace_transfer_of_combrooted_optical_frequencies_over_an_18-km_openair_link_nature_communications/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/freespace_transfer_of_combrooted_optical_frequencies_over_an_18-km_openair_link_nature_communications/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2019-10-17&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: Nature Communications&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: Phase-coherent transfer of optical frequencies over a long distance is required for diverse photonic applications, including optical clock dissemination and physical constants measurement. Several demonstrations were made successfully over fiber networks, but not much work has been done yet through the open air where atmospheric turbulence prevails. Here, the authors use an 18 km outdoor link to transmit multiple optical carriers extracted directly from a frequency comb of a 4.2 THz spectral width. In stabilization to a high-finesse cavity with a 1.5 Hz linewidth, the comb-rooted optical carriers are simultaneously transferred with collective suppression of atmospheric phase noise to −80 dBc Hz−1. Microwaves are also delivered by pairing two separate optical carriers bound with inter-comb-mode coherence, for example a 10 GHz signal with phase noise of −105 dBc Hz−1 at 1 Hz offset. Lastly, an add-on demonstration is given for multi-channel coherent optical communications with the potential of multi-Tbps data transmission in free space.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Hyun Jay Kang, Jaewon Yang, Byung Jae Chun, Heesuk Jang, Byung Soo Kim, Young-Jin Kim &amp;amp; Seung-Woo Kim&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-12443-8">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-12443-8&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Multi-immersion open-top light-sheet microscope for high-throughput imaging of cleared tissues</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/multiimmersion_opentop_lightsheet_microscope_for_highthroughput_imaging_of_cleared_tissues_nature_communications/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/multiimmersion_opentop_lightsheet_microscope_for_highthroughput_imaging_of_cleared_tissues_nature_communications/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2019-07-29&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: Nature Communications&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: Recent advances in optical clearing and light-sheet microscopy have provided unprecedented access to structural and molecular information from intact tissues. However, current light-sheet microscopes have imposed constraints on the size, shape, number of specimens, and compatibility with various clearing protocols. In this paper the authors present a multi-immersion open-top light-sheet microscope that enables simple mounting of multiple specimens processed with a variety of clearing protocols, which will facilitate wide adoption by preclinical researchers and clinical laboratories.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Adam K. Glaser, Nicholas P. Reder, Ye Chen, Chengbo Yin, Linpeng Wei, Soyoung Kang, Lindsey A. Barner, Weisi Xie, Erin F. McCarty, Chenyi Mao, Aaron R. Halpern, Caleb R. Stoltzfus, Jonathan S. Daniels, Michael Y. Gerner, Philip R. Nicovich, Joshua C. Vaughan, Lawrence D. True &amp;amp; Jonathan T. C. Liu&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-10534-0">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-10534-0&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Automating multimodal microscopy with NanoJ-Fluidics</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/automating_multimodal_microscopy_with_nanojfluidics_nature_communications/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/automating_multimodal_microscopy_with_nanojfluidics_nature_communications/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2019-05-02&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: Nature Communications&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: Channel Editor Summary: The authors have developed an open source and low-cost device for automated control of labelling and washing cells while under the microscope. This makes imaging it much easier to implement multiple step procedures for imaging at a high temporal and spatial resolution on any microscope with high reproducibility. The paper goes on to demonstrate very successful use in super-resolution imaging of actin bundles during cell-shape changes. The NanoJ-Fluidics device is built from LEGO components and nicknamed (of course) Pumpy McPumpface.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Pedro Almada, Pedro M. Pereira, Siân Culley, Ghislaine Caillol, Fanny Boroni-Rueda, Christina L. Dix, Guillaume Charras, Buzz Baum, Romain F. Laine, Christophe Leterrier &amp;amp; Ricardo Henriques&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-09231-9">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-09231-9&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>