<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>PLOS Biology | Open Source Toolkit</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/tag/plos-biology/</link><atom:link href="https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/tag/plos-biology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>PLOS Biology</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>CC BY SA 4.0</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/media/openneuroscience_logo_dark.svg</url><title>PLOS Biology</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/tag/plos-biology/</link></image><item><title>Leveraging open hardware to alleviate the burden of COVID-19 on global health systems</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/leveraging_open_hardware_to_alleviate_the_burden_of_covid19_on_global_health_systems_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/leveraging_open_hardware_to_alleviate_the_burden_of_covid19_on_global_health_systems_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2020-05-06&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: With the current rapid spread of COVID-19, global health systems are increasingly overburdened by the sheer number of people that need diagnosis, isolation and treatment. Shortcomings are evident across the board, from staffing, facilities for rapid and reliable testing to availability of hospital beds and key medical-grade equipment. The scale and breadth of the problem calls for an equally substantive response not only from frontline workers such as medical staff and scientists, but from skilled members of the public who have the time, facilities and knowledge to meaningfully contribute to a consolidated global response. Here, the authors summarise community-driven approaches based on Free and Open Source scientific and medical Hardware as well as personal protective equipment currently being developed and deployed to support the global response for COVID-19 prevention, patient treatment and diagnostics.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Andre Maia Chagas, Jennifer C. Molloy, Lucia L. Prieto-Godino, Tom Baden&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.3000730&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ElectroPen: An ultra-low–cost, electricity-free, portable electroporator</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/electropen_an_ultralowcost_electricityfree_portable_electroporator_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/electropen_an_ultralowcost_electricityfree_portable_electroporator_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2020-02-07&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: None&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Gaurav Byagathvalli, Soham Sinha, Yan Zhang, Mark P. Styczynski, Janet Standeven, M. Saad Bhamla&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.3000589&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Knowledge-guided analysis of omics data using the KnowEnG cloud platform</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/knowledgeguided_analysis_of_omics_data_using_the_knoweng_cloud_platform_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/knowledgeguided_analysis_of_omics_data_using_the_knoweng_cloud_platform_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2020-01-23&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: None&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Charles Blatti III, Amin Emad, Matthew J. Berry, Lisa Gatzke, Milt Epstein, Daniel Lanier, Pramod Rizal, Jing Ge, Xiaoxia Liao, Omar Sobh, Mike Lambert, Corey S. Post, Jinfeng Xiao, Peter Groves, Aidan T. Epstein, Xi Chen, Subhashini Srinivasan, Erik Lehnert, Krishna R. Kalari, Liewei Wang, Richard M. Weinshilboum, Jun S. Song, C. Victor Jongeneel, Jiawei Han, Umberto Ravaioli, Nahil Sobh, Colleen B. Bushell, Saurabh Sinha&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.3000583&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Nessys: A new set of tools for the automated detection of nuclei within intact tissues and dense 3D cultures</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/nessys_a_new_set_of_tools_for_the_automated_detection_of_nuclei_within_intact_tissues_and_dense_3d_cultures_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/nessys_a_new_set_of_tools_for_the_automated_detection_of_nuclei_within_intact_tissues_and_dense_3d_cultures_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2019-09-26&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: Methods for measuring the properties of individual cells within their native 3D environment will enable a deeper understanding of embryonic development, tissue regeneration, and tumorigenesis. However, current methods for segmenting nuclei in 3D tissues are not designed for situations in which nuclei are densely packed, nonspherical, or heterogeneous in shape, size, or texture, all of which are true of many embryonic and adult tissue types as well as in many cases for cells differentiating in culture. The authors provide a 3D editor and inspector for the manual curation of the segmentation results as well as a program to assess the accuracy of the segmentation. Blin et al. have also generated a live reporter of the NE that can be used to track live cells in 3 dimensions over time. The authors use this to monitor the history of cell interactions and occurrences of neighbour exchange within cultures of pluripotent cells during differentiation. The authors provide these tools in an open-access user-friendly format.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Guillaume Blin, Daina Sadurska, Rosa Portero Migueles, Naiming Chen, Julia A. Watson, Sally Lowell&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.3000388&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Nesting box imager: Contact-free, real-time measurement of activity, surface body temperature, and respiratory rate applied to hibernating mouse models</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/nesting_box_imager_contactfree_realtime_measurement_of_activity_surface_body_temperature_and_respiratory_rate_applied_to_hibernating_mouse_models_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/nesting_box_imager_contactfree_realtime_measurement_of_activity_surface_body_temperature_and_respiratory_rate_applied_to_hibernating_mouse_models_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2019-09-05&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: If you&amp;rsquo;re trying to measure animal activity without disturbing a hibernating animal your options were previously limited and expensive but the growing utility and shrinking price of sensors, cameras and single-board computers has enabled this device for monitoring mice nesting boxes using a Raspberry Pi and an infrared camera for under $400. The authors demonstrate the use of contact-free measurement of respiration rate, movement and surface body temperature with data logging and processing (so long as the mouse doesn&amp;rsquo;t block the camera with bedding!).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Nathaniel E. Kallmyer, Han Jong Shin, Ethan A. Brem, William J. Israelsen, Nigel F. Reuel&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.3000406&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Harnessing robotic automation and web-based technologies to modernize scientific outreach</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/harnessing_robotic_automation_and_webbased_technologies_to_modernize_scientific_outreach_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/harnessing_robotic_automation_and_webbased_technologies_to_modernize_scientific_outreach_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2019-07-29&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: Technological breakthroughs in the past two decades have ushered in a new era of biomedical research, turning it into an information-rich and technology-driven science. This scientific revolution, though evident to the research community, remains opaque to nonacademic audiences. Such knowledge gaps are likely to persist without revised strategies for science education and public outreach. To address this challenge, the authors developed a unique outreach program to actively engage over 100 high-school students in the investigation of multidrug-resistant bacteria. The program uses robotic automation and interactive web-based tools to bridge geographical distances, scale up the number of participants, and reduce overall cost.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Orna Dahan, Bat-Shahar Dorfman, Serkan Sayin, Brittany Rosener, Tiffany Hua, Anat Yarden, Amir Mitchell&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.3000348&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Scientific Community Image Forum: A discussion forum for scientific image software</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/scientific_community_image_forum_a_discussion_forum_for_scientific_image_software_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/scientific_community_image_forum_a_discussion_forum_for_scientific_image_software_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2019-07-04&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: Channel Editor Summary: In open source software, open code and free software is only the tip of the iceberg. Successful open source projects tend to have strong communities supporting both contributors as well as users - but this often comes with the hidden cost in volunteer (or staff) time and resources. The Scientific Community Image Forum helps to mitigate this concern by creating a single common forum for scientific imaging software that spans many domains and open source projects, and provides imaging software users with access to a broad range of experts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Curtis T. Rueden, Jeanelle Ackerman, Ellen T. Arena, Jan Eglinger, Beth A. Cimini, Allen Goodman, Anne E. Carpenter, Kevin W. Eliceiri&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.3000340&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A 3D-printed hand-powered centrifuge for molecular biology</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/a_3dprinted_handpowered_centrifuge_for_molecular_biology_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/a_3dprinted_handpowered_centrifuge_for_molecular_biology_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2019-06-17&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: None&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Gaurav Byagathvalli, Aaron Pomerantz, Soham Sinha, Janet Standeven, M. Saad Bhamla&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: &lt;a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3000251">https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3000251&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Low-cost (&lt;€5), open-source, potential alternative to commercial spectrophotometers</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/lowcost_5_opensource_potential_alternative_to_commercial_spectrophotometers_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/lowcost_5_opensource_potential_alternative_to_commercial_spectrophotometers_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2019-06-12&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: None&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Vasco Ribeiro Pereira, Bill Stephen Hosker&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.3000321&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bio-On-Magnetic-Beads (BOMB): Open platform for high-throughput nucleic acid extraction and manipulation</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/bioonmagneticbeads_bomb_open_platform_for_highthroughput_nucleic_acid_extraction_and_manipulation_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/bioonmagneticbeads_bomb_open_platform_for_highthroughput_nucleic_acid_extraction_and_manipulation_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2019-02-01&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: Channel Editor Summary: Open-source, scalable and high-throughput protocols for purifying DNA and RNA using magnetic beads are presented, providing easy to use methods for some of the most common processes in molecular biology. The authors include detailed comparisons to other methods and extremely in-depth documentation to enable researchers to use and build upon the protocols plus a webpage and forum for community engagement. This paper provides a blueprint for documenting open source biology projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Phil Oberacker, Peter Stepper, Donna M. Bond, Sven Höhn, Jule Focken, Vivien Meyer, Luca Schelle, Victoria J. Sugrue, Gert-Jan Jeunen, Tim Moser, Steven R. Hore, Ferdinand von Meyenn, Katharina Hipp, Timothy A. Hore, Tomasz P. Jurkowski&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.3000107&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Enabling precision medicine via standard communication of HTS provenance, analysis, and results</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/enabling_precision_medicine_via_standard_communication_of_hts_provenance_analysis_and_results_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/enabling_precision_medicine_via_standard_communication_of_hts_provenance_analysis_and_results_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2019-01-17&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: A personalized approach based on a patient&amp;rsquo;s or pathogen’s unique genomic sequence is the foundation of precision medicine. Genomic findings must be robust and reproducible, and experimental data capture should adhere to findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable (FAIR) guiding principles. Moreover, effective precision medicine requires standardized reporting that extends beyond wet-lab procedures to computational methods. The BioCompute framework enables standardized reporting of genomic sequence data provenance, including provenance domain, usability domain, execution domain, verification kit, and error domain. This framework facilitates communication and promotes interoperability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Gil Alterovitz, Dennis Dean, Carole Goble, Michael R. Crusoe, Stian Soiland-Reyes, Amanda Bell, Anais Hayes, Anita Suresh, Anjan Purkayastha, Charles H. King, Dan Taylor, Elaine Johanson, Elaine E. Thompson, Eric Donaldson, Hiroki Morizono, Hsinyi Tsang, Jeet K. Vora, Jeremy Goecks, Jianchao Yao, Jonas S. Almeida, Jonathon Keeney, KanakaDurga Addepalli, Konstantinos Krampis, Krista M. Smith, Lydia Guo, Mark Walderhaug, Marco Schito, Matthew Ezewudo, Nuria Guimera, Paul Walsh, Robel Kahsay, Srikanth Gottipati, Timothy C. Rodwell, Toby Bloom, Yuching Lai, Vahan Simonyan, Raja Mazumder&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.3000099&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Spikeling: A low-cost hardware implementation of a spiking neuron for neuroscience teaching and outreach</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/spikeling_a_lowcost_hardware_implementation_of_a_spiking_neuron_for_neuroscience_teaching_and_outreach_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/spikeling_a_lowcost_hardware_implementation_of_a_spiking_neuron_for_neuroscience_teaching_and_outreach_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2018-11-19&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: Spikeling provides an in silico model of a spiking neuron that can be used to illustrate their biophysical behaviour through sound and light inputs and outputs as well as a custom oscilloscope interface. The authors evaluate the device in both Nigeria and the UK and provide exciting examples of potential uses from the classroom through to graduate study and public outreach. The ability to chain Spikelings together adds an extra dimension that opens up opportunities for experimentation with networks of neurons.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Tom Baden, Ben James, Maxime J. Y. Zimmermann, Phillip Bartel, Dorieke Grijseels, Thomas Euler, Leon Lagnado, Miguel Maravall&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.2006760&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Haves and have nots must find a better way: The case for open scientific hardware</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/haves_and_have_nots_must_find_a_better_way_the_case_for_open_scientific_hardware_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/haves_and_have_nots_must_find_a_better_way_the_case_for_open_scientific_hardware_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2018-09-27&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: Many efforts are making science more open and accessible; they are mostly concentrated on issues that appear before and after experiments are performed: open access journals, open databases, and many other tools to increase reproducibility of science and access to information. However, these initiatives do not promote access to scientific equipment necessary for experiments. Mostly due to monetary constraints, equipment availability has always been uneven around the globe, affecting predominantly low-income countries and institutions. Here, a case is made for the use of free open source hardware in research and education, including countries and institutions where funds were never the biggest problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Andre Maia Chagas&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: &lt;a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3000014">https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3000014&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Digital open science—Teaching digital tools for reproducible and transparent research</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/digital_open_scienceteaching_digital_tools_for_reproducible_and_transparent_research_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/digital_open_scienceteaching_digital_tools_for_reproducible_and_transparent_research_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2018-07-26&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: An important hallmark of science is the transparency and reproducibility of scientific results. Over the last few years, internet-based technologies have emerged that allow for a representation of the scientific process that goes far beyond traditional methods and analysis descriptions. Using these often freely available tools requires a suite of skills that is not necessarily part of a curriculum in the life sciences. To close this gap, Toelch and Ostwald have designed an introductory course that guides students towards a reproducible science workflow. This paper outlines the course content and possible extensions, report encountered challenges, and discuss how to integrate such a course in existing curricula.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Ulf Toelch, Dirk Ostwald&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.2006022">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.2006022&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CellProfiler 3.0: Next-generation image processing for biology</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/cellprofiler_30_nextgeneration_image_processing_for_biology_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/cellprofiler_30_nextgeneration_image_processing_for_biology_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2018-07-03&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: CellProfiler is a free software that has enabled researchers, without training in computer vision or programming community to create flexible, modular image analysis pipelines since its release in 2005. In this article the authors introduce CellProfiler 3.0 which now enables analysis of three-dimensional (3D) image stacks, provides a protocol for cloud-based, large-scale image processing and enables running pre trained deep learning models on images.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CellProfiler is an exceptional open source package which follows best practices and has created a large active community. Their GitHub repository has currently more than 2,000 closed issues, 1,045 closed pull requests and 41 contributors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Claire McQuin, Allen Goodman, Vasiliy Chernyshev, Lee Kamentsky, Beth A. Cimini, Kyle W. Karhohs, Minh Doan, Liya Ding, Susanne M. Rafelski, Derek Thirstrup, Winfried Wiegraebe, Shantanu Singh, Tim Becker, Juan C. Caicedo, Anne E. Carpenter&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: &lt;a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.2005970">https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.2005970&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Imagining the “open” university: Sharing scholarship to improve research and education</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/imagining_the_open_university_sharing_scholarship_to_improve_research_and_education_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/imagining_the_open_university_sharing_scholarship_to_improve_research_and_education_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2017-10-24&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: Open scholarship, such as the sharing of articles, code, data, and educational resources, has the potential to improve university research and education as well as increase the impact universities can have beyond their own walls. The author proposes several concrete actions universities could take to support open scholarship and outline ways in which such initiatives could benefit the public as well as institutions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Erin C. McKiernan&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.1002614&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ethoscopes: An open platform for high-throughput ethomics</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/ethoscopes_an_open_platform_for_highthroughput_ethomics_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/ethoscopes_an_open_platform_for_highthroughput_ethomics_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2017-10-19&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: This design is a rig for high-throughput behavioural experiments with genetically amenable model species such as fruit flies. At its core, it is a webcam (RPi camera) focussed at a set of interchangable behavioural arena arrays for parallel recording of multiple aninals at once. Laden with a light zapper for optogenetics, and a nice networking interface for controlling multiple units from a remote computer this looks like a great tool for high throughput ethomics!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Quentin Geissmann, Luis Garcia Rodriguez, Esteban J. Beckwith, Alice S. French, Arian R. Jamasb, Giorgio F. Gilestro&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.2003026&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The €100 lab: A 3D-printable open-source platform for fluorescence microscopy, optogenetics, and accurate temperature control during behaviour of zebrafish, Drosophila, and Caenorhabditis elegans</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/the_100_lab_a_3dprintable_opensource_platform_for_fluorescence_microscopy_optogenetics_and_accurate_temperature_control_during_behaviour_of_zebrafish_drosophila_and_caenorhabditis_elegans_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/the_100_lab_a_3dprintable_opensource_platform_for_fluorescence_microscopy_optogenetics_and_accurate_temperature_control_during_behaviour_of_zebrafish_drosophila_and_caenorhabditis_elegans_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2017-07-18&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: The paper describes a €100 portable and neurogenetics lab. Built with off the shelf components and 3D printed parts it is a versatile tool that due to its modular design can be useful in different fields. So far proof-of-principle experiments show that it can be used for neuroscience research, medical diagnostics and education.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Andre Maia Chagas, Lucia L. Prieto-Godino, Aristides B. Arrenberg, Tom Baden&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.2002702&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CuboCube: Student creation of a cancer genetics e-textbook using open-access software for social learning</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/cubocube_student_creation_of_a_cancer_genetics_etextbook_using_openaccess_software_for_social_learning_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/cubocube_student_creation_of_a_cancer_genetics_etextbook_using_openaccess_software_for_social_learning_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2017-03-07&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: CuboCube is an open-source learning materials creation system designed to facilitate e-textbook development, with an ultimate goal of improving the social learning experience for students. Equipped with crowdsourcing capabilities, CuboCube provides intuitive tools for nontechnical and technical authors alike to create content together in a structured manner. The process of e-textbook development revealed both strengths and challenges of the approach, which can inform future efforts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Puya Seid-Karbasi, Xin C. Ye, Allen W. Zhang, Nicole Gladish, Suzanne Y. S. Cheng, Katharina Rothe, Jessica A. Pilsworth, Min A. Kang, Natalie Doolittle, Xiaoyan Jiang, Peter C. Stirling, Wyeth W. Wasserman&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.2001192&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Biotic Game Design Project for Integrated Life Science and Engineering Education</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/a_biotic_game_design_project_for_integrated_life_science_and_engineering_education_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/a_biotic_game_design_project_for_integrated_life_science_and_engineering_education_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2015-03-25&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: None&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Nate J. Cira, Alice M. Chung, Aleksandra K. Denisin, Stefano Rensi, Gabriel N. Sanchez, Stephen R. Quake, Ingmar H. Riedel-Kruse&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.1002110&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Open Labware: 3-D Printing Your Own Lab Equipment</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/open_labware_3d_printing_your_own_lab_equipment_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/open_labware_3d_printing_your_own_lab_equipment_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2015-03-20&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: None&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Tom Baden, Andre Maia Chagas, Greg Gage, Timothy Marzullo, Lucia L. Prieto-Godino, Thomas Euler&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.1002086&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Billion Cell Construct: Will Three-Dimensional Printing Get Us There?</title><link>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/the_billion_cell_construct_will_threedimensional_printing_get_us_there_plos_biology/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://amchagas.github.io/open-source-toolkit/post/the_billion_cell_construct_will_threedimensional_printing_get_us_there_plos_biology/</guid><description>&lt;p>Publishing date: 2014-06-17&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published on: PLOS Biology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>summary: None&lt;/p>
&lt;p>authors: Jordan S. Miller&lt;/p>
&lt;p>link to paper: 10.1371/journal.pbio.1001882&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Icons made by &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/free-icon/bookshelves_3576884" title="catkuro">catkuro&lt;/a> from &lt;a href="https://www.flaticon.com/" title="Flaticon"> &lt;a href="http://www.flaticon.com">www.flaticon.com&lt;/a>&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>